Guide to the Mark Perlberg Papers 1953-2010
University of Chicago Library
Perlberg, Mark. Papers
1953-2010
3 linear feet (3 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Mark Perlberg (b. 1929, d. June 23rd, 2008) was a poet, journalist, editor, and educator. In 1968, he co-founded the Poetry Center of Chicago. The collection consists of event announcements and correspondence related to the Poetry Center, materials used in Perlberg’s poetry workshop at the Newberry Library, and drafts of Perlberg’s various essays and poems. In addition, there are posters from Poetry Center events, including two that are autographed (one by Stanley Kunitz and another by Galway Kinnell). Materials date from 1953 to 2010.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Mark Perlberg was born in 1929 in Palisade, New Jersey. In 1950, he graduated from Hobart College with a degree in English Literature. While taking graduate courses at Columbia University in 1952, he was called to serve in the Korean War. In 1953, he married Anna Backer and, in 1954, he was discharged from the service. He then began his career as a journalist with Time Magazine, relocating to Chicago in 1956. He later worked for Encyclopaedia Britannica, World Book Encyclopedia, and Prism. During this time, he and Anna had two daughters, Katherine Eve and Julie Anna. In 1968, he co-founded the Poetry Center of Chicago, serving as president for 13 years. He also taught a poetry workshop at the Newberry Library for nearly 20 years. Perlberg has five published poetry collections: The Burning Field (1970), The Feel of the Sun (1981), The Impossible Toystore (2000), Waiting for the Alchemist (2009), and Theater of Memory: New and Selected Poems (2012). Mark Perlberg died on June 23rd, 2008 in Skokie, Illinois. His wife, Anna, was instrumental in bringing his final collection to publication.
Scope Note
The Mark Perlberg Papers are organized into 7 series:
Series I: Personal Papers; this series contains some of Perlberg’s important personal documents, including his military discharge papers, permissions and copyright information for his published works, and a copy of his birth certificate. Materials date from 1953 to circa 2008 and are arranged chronologically.
Series II: Correspondence; this series contains Perlberg’s personal as well as profession correspondence. The bulk of his personal correspondence is in regards to his poetry while the bulk of his professional correspondence consists of official communications between the Poetry Center of Chicago and various other institutions, including the Museum of Contemporary Art and the School of the Art Institute of Chicago. Materials date from 1967 to 2010 and are arranged first by type (personal followed by professional), then chronologically.
Series III: Writings; this series contains typescript and holograph drafts of Perlberg’s various essays and poems. Materials date from 1965 to 2008 and are arranged first by type (essays followed by poems), then alphabetically by title.
Series IV: Publicity and Reviews; this series contains publicity information and advertisements as well as literary reviews of Perlberg’s poetry. Materials date from 1977 to 2010 and are arranged first by type (publicity followed by reviews), then alphabetically by the title of the work being reviewed.
Series V: Poetry Center of Chicago; this series contains numerous documents pertaining to the administration of the Poetry Center of Chicago, including an annual report, development prospectus, and event announcements. Materials date from 1978 to 2001 and are arranged chronologically.
Series VI: Newberry Library, Poetry Workshop; this series contains mostly course plans, pamphlets, and course evaluations of Perlberg’s poetry workshop sponsored by the Newberry Library. Materials date from 1986 to 2003 and are arranged chronologically.
Series VII: Oversize; this series contains newspaper clippings of reviews for Perlberg’s book entitled The Burning Field as well as posters for events hosted by Poetry Center of Chicago in its early years. Also included is a photograph of the Poetry Center founders. Materials date from 1970 to circa 1980 and are arranged chronologically.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Poetry Center of Chicago. Records
Chicago Review. Records
Poetry: A Magazine of Verse. Records
Subject Headings
Perlberg, Mark, 1929-; Poetry Center of Chicago; Museum of Contemporary Art (Chicago, Ill.); School of the Art Institute of Chicago; Newberry Library; Illinois Arts Council; Poetry
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - Letter of Recommendation (from van Doren), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Military Discharge Papers, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copyrights and Permissions, 1976-2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Birth Certificate (copy), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Information and CV – Typescript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Perlberg, Mark (regarding his writing and editing), 1967-2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Perlberg, Mark (regarding Lannan Residency), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Perlberg, Mark (regarding his death), 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Poetry Center – General, 1975-2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Poetry Center – Illinois Arts Council, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Poetry Center – John Cage Benefit, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Poetry Center – Museum of Contemporary Art, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Poetry Center – School of the Art Institute of Chicago, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series III: Writings
  - Essays – Autobiographical Essay – Typescript draft with holograph notes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Essays – “The Growth and Popularity of Poetry Workshops” – Typescript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Essays – “Janacek’s Diary of One Who Vanished” – Typescript draft, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Essays – “Some Thoughts on Translating Chinese Poetry” – Typescript drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Poems – “The Garden” and other poems – Typescript and holograph drafts, 1965-1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Poems – “Nightsweat” and other poems – Typescript and holograph drafts, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Poems – “Odyssey Variations” and other poems – Typescript and holograph drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Poems – “Song of the Platelets” – Typescript and holograph drafts, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series IV: Publicity and Reviews
  - Publicity – Flyers, newsletters, clippings, holograph notes, 1977-2005 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Publicity – Postcard – Theater of Memory, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Reviews – The Burning Field, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Reviews – The Feel of the Sun, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Reviews – The Impossible Toystore, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Reviews – Sunflower Splendor and Poems for the Dead, 1975-1984 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Reviews – Waiting for the Alchemist, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Series V: Poetry Center of Chicago
  - Seasonal programs, 1978-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual report, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Program evaluation report, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Resolution by members and board of directors, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Event announcements, 1986-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Event programs, 1988-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lists of readers and contributors, circa 1988-2008 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Long range plan and development prospectus, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Introductions for visiting writers, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series VI: Newberry Library, Poetry Workshop
  - Pamphlets, 1986-2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Student poems – Typescript drafts with holograph comments, circa 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Course plans – Typescript drafts and holograph notes, 1995-2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Seminar evaluations, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Poems for class, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series VII: Oversize
  - Reviews – The Burning Field – Newspaper Clippings, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Poetry Center – Event posters, circa 1970-1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Poetry Center – Photograph of founders, including Mark Perlberg, circa 1970-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)